RG 003, New London County, County Court Files
Connecticut State Library
New London County, County Court files
1691-1855
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. County Court (New London County)
217.25 cubic feet
Files hold the most detailed information available on a particular case. Files usually contain a summons or writ, a document that contains a variety of other useful information, and often one or more additional documents, such as a debt by note, debt by bond, a list of book debts, depositions and/or testimony of witnesses, pleadings by lawyers, power of attorney, an accounting of court costs, and occasionally summonses for witnesses and a copy of the jury verdict.
RG003_NLCC_Files
1921-025
Historical Note
The first Connecticut judicial proceedings probably took place on April 26, 1636, at "A Corte holden in Newtown" [Hartford] under the commission granted to eight leaders of the infant colony by the General Court of Massachusetts.
In 1638, the General Court established the Particular Court (often called the "Quarter Court" because it was required to meet every three months). While the General Court, later called the General Assembly, controlled the administration of justice, the Particular Court was the colony's principal judicial body until King Charles II granted Connecticut its Charter in 1662. Under the new Charter, the Particular Court was abolished and two new levels of courts established: the Court of Assistants in 1665 and county courts in 1666. Separate probate courts were established in 1698.1
County courts, often called courts of common pleas, existed from 1666 until 1855, when the General Assembly, controlled by Know Nothings, streamlined the State's "bloated judiciary system" which represented the largest public expense by eliminating the county courts and dividing its jurisdiction between the superior court and local town courts.2 This new two-tiered court system proved to be impractical and new courts of common pleas for each county were established as early as 1870.
County courts considered appeals of from local justice courts and had original jurisdiction to try all civil and criminal cases except those concerning "life, limb, banishment, adultery, or divorce." In the colonial era, all suits for debt for sums greater than forty shillings were heard by the county court, a sum increased to $35 by the early nineteenth century and $50 by mid-century. The county courts served as the "workhorses of the Connecticut judicial system" and usually met three times per year.3
The New London County Court was organized in 1666, but the first files do not appear until 1691. Prior to the existence of files, information on court actions can only be tracked through bound volumes of Trials.4 Files become comprehensive in the first decade of the eighteenth century, but are not extant for the period between February 1775 and June 1781 due to the fact that they were destroyed in a British raid on New London and Groton under the leadership of Benedict Arnold on September 6, 1781.
New London County did not have a single shire town and sessions of the court alternated between New London and Norwich. County boundaries changed over time, but for most of the colonial period the court had jurisdiction over the towns of Groton, Killingworth, Lyme, New London, Norwich, Preston, Saybrook, and Stonington.5 After the Revolution, Killingworth and Saybrook became parts of newly formed Middlesex County and Colchester moved from Hartford to New London County. In addition, Montville was hived off from New London in 1786 and Waterford from New London in 1801, and Bozrah, Franklin, and Lisbon formed from Norwich in 1786. Other new towns formed in the nineteenth century were North Stonington (1807), Griswold (1815), Salem (1819), Ledyard (1836), and East Lyme (1839). Lebanon moved from Windham to New London County in 1823.
Court personnel consisted of the chief judge and four justices of the peace et quorum appointed annual by the General Assembly at its May session, the county clerk and county treasurer chosen by the court, jurors from the several towns in the county, plus the sheriff, deputy sheriffs, and the jailors for the New London and Norwich jails.
Endnotes
1 The Superior Court established in 1711 replaced the Court of Assistants.
2 Mark Voss-Hubbard, Beyond Party: Cultures of Antipartisanship in Northern Politics before the Civil War (Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 2002), 150.
3 Dwight Loomis and J. Gilbert Calhoun, The Judicial and Civil History of Connecticut (Boston: The Boston History Company, 1895), 128-36, 155-56; Bruce H. Mann, Neighbors and Strangers: Law and Community in Early Connecticut (Chapel Hill, NC: The University of North Carolina Press, 1987), 7-8. The phrase "workhorses of the Connecticut judicial system" comes from Mann, Neighbors and Strangers, page 8. The General Assembly served as the Supreme Court until replaced by the Supreme Court of Errors in the 1780s.
4 Bound volumes of Trials do not exist for the periods between 1704 and 1710 and 1769 through June 1781.
5 Canterbury, Killingly, Lebanon, Plainfield, and Voluntown were included within the bounds of New London County until the establishment of Windham County in 1726.
Using Court Records
Court records present difficulties for researchers. Physical condition represents the first and greatest challenge. Prior to this processing project, Files for New London County were folded several times to fit into a standard size with second and third documents for the same case wrapped inside the first document. In addition, many were torn or in poor physical condition. Although these difficulties have been overcome, intellectual access still presents a challenge.
Researchers must examine papers in several different locations in order to gather all materials on a given person or subject. First, Dockets need to be examined. They may be found either bound with volumes of Trials, separate boxes of manuscript dockets, or in five volumes of Dockets covering the period between 1835 and 1855. Dockets generally include the names of the plaintiff and defendant, information on the disposition of the case (withdrawn, continued, execution granted, etc.), and information (usually a docket number) on where to find more detailed data. Often surnames of the lawyer or lawyers are also included. Second comes Trials, located in bound volumes. They usually contain a short paragraph that summarizes the nature and disposition of each case.153 Third, Files hold the most detailed information available on a particular case. Files usually contain a summons or writ, a document that contains a variety of other useful information, and often one or more additional documents, such as a debt by note, debt by bond, a list of book debts, depositions and/or testimony of witnesses, pleadings by lawyers, power of attorney, an accounting of court costs, and occasionally summonses for witnesses and a copy of the jury verdict. The overwhelming majority of cases consist of one or two documents. A fourth places in which researchers may need to look under some circumstances is Papers by Subject. Consisting of materials removed from Files after the records were transferred to the State Library in 1921, three series in particular may have to be examined for further information; Costs, Executions, and Summons for Evidence. If the losing party in a case did not accept the verdict of the county court, then it was appealed to the Superior Court and same three sources examined to follow the case to its conclusion.154
Separate docket volumes first appear in New London County in December 1835. Prior to that time, one has to search through the volumes of Trials to the docket section found immediately before the records for each court session.155 Unfortunately, the existence of a docket for a case does not necessarily mean that trial or file information is available. If a case was withdrawn or the plaintiff failed to appear, then usually nothing exists in Trials, although documentation is generally found in Files. To make matters more complicated, beginning with the court session for June 1744, no docket cases are found in a separate A-Z alphabetical listing following the numerical run of decided cases. Often these no docket cases are listed somewhere in the docket section of Trials, but not necessarily at the court session that these materials appear. For example, a case that is ultimately withdrawn may be listed in the docket pages of Trials for one session of the court and the papers themselves found in the records of a later session.
Sometimes the disposition of a case is found in Trials and nothing appears in Files. On rare occasions, the only source for information on a case is found in Dockets. Researchers, therefore, must examine all three sources but, if research gold is to be discovered, it will generally be found in Files. A great deal of valuable information can be found in no docket or non-adjudicated cases. For example, Thomas Wait of Lyme sued Nathaniel Beckwith for £23 for failure to deliver ten ewes, ten lambs, and twenty pounds of wool to the plaintiff by June 1, 1741. Titus Hurlbut of New London sought damages in February 1742 from William Lamson for not framing the plaintiff's house as per contract.156
Although Trials and Files contain the most useful information on lawsuits, certain series of Papers by Subject provide valuable supplementary documentation. Costs, Executions, and Summons for Evidence are the ones that relate most directly to Trials, although other series contain valuable data. See the finding aid to Papers by Subject for detailed information. Costs give detail on the specifics of the expenses incurred in cases, while Executions provide information on the collection of debts and Summons for Evidence provides the names of people called to testify in contested court cases.
Endnotes
153The volumes for Files, in addition to containing docket information, also often include lists of cases continued and adjourned, plus accounts of court expenses, names of court officers, and licenses for tanners and tavernkeepers.
154Papers by Subject consist of materials on a variety of other subjects, like Admissions to the Bar, Conservators and Guardians, Costs, Executions, Indians, and Travel. They are identified by cross-reference slips of paper usually found at the beginning of Files for each court session. The x-ref card gives the name or subject of the case, the subject to which it has been transferred, the original docket number of the case, and a new file number in pencil for the case.
155Five boxes of manuscript Dockets exist for the years 1730-1835. Since the same information is included in the volumes of Trials before each session of the court, it is not recommended that researches spend time consulting this source.
156Thomas Wait v. Nathaniel Beckwith, NLCC Files, Nov. 1741, Box 70, folder 5, no. 570; Titus Hurlbut v. William Lamson, Ibid, Feb. 1742, Box 70, folder 21, no. 230.
Scope and Content
Researchers need to be aware in studying these records that the spelling of surnames often varies. It could be Ames or Eames, Hide or Hyde, Lathrop or Lothrop, Maynor, Maynard, Minerd, or Mynard, Right or Wright, or Waterhouse, Waterus, or Watrous, to cite just a few examples.
The first file document dates from 1691, but Files only begin to be frequent enough to adequately supplement and expand on the information found in the Trials volumes in the first decade of the eighteenth century. As a general rule, Files contain much more information about cases than can be found in bound volumes of Trials, but it is necessary for researchers to consult both sources in order to obtain complete overviews of cases.
Many subjects are addressed in the records of the New London County Court. The overwhelming majority of cases for much of the history of the court, around 85-90%, consist of suits for debt - debt by bond, debt by book, and debt by note. By the end of the first quarter of the 19th century, however, State criminal prosecutions increase both in number and percentage of the total for each session. In many instances, the nature of the bond, book, or note is not found in the records. Occasionally, however, the file papers state that the debt by note or writing, as an example, is for the delivery of a named product or service in return for value received by the defendant. Although debt cases appear routine and uninteresting to the uninitiated, they contain much valuable information. The writ or summons, often a printed form with spaces filled in by hand, gives the name of plaintiff and defendant, the nature and amount of debt, the date of the writ, and the name of the justice of the peace, assistant, or clerk who completes and signs the document.
The reverse of the writ generally contains a note by a constable of sheriff's deputy confirming that the document has been served on the defendant and it includes information on how it was served. The constable or deputy may leave a copy of the writ at the defendant's usual place of residence, may read it out in the defendant's presence, may take an appearance bond to make certain that the defendant responds to the summons, may attach land or personal property to cover twice the amount of the debt to insure the defendant's appearance, or may take an insolvent defendant off to jail. A typical attachment of land is as follows: "I attached Two pieces of Land Situat[ed] in the North Society of Lyme at a place Known by the Name of Joshuas Town and is bounded (viz) first piece Southerly by Eight Mile River East by Land belonging to Elisha Sheldon, Esqr Northerly part by a Ledge & partly by Land belonging to Ezra Brockway & westerly by Ezra Brockway."6 The reverse of the summons also includes docketing information, often a listing of constable expenses, and sometimes pleadings by lawyers representing one or both parties in the case.
In cases of debt by note or writing, often the original contract between the two parties is included in court documentation. The note is signed by the person borrowing the funds or promising to perform the service and usually contains the signatures of two witnesses. This information is valuable for those interested in studying literacy in early Connecticut and the nature of personal relationships between the two parties. Debts by bond often include the original bond and debts by book sometimes provide a list of debts owed by the defendant to the plaintiff. These lists, although representing a distinct minority of book cases, contain valuable information detailing the goods purchased from a shopkeeper or merchant.
Once in a while an unusual debt case is brought before the court, as in William Kerr v. Roland Rogers, July 1753. The plaintiff sold Rogers a yoke of oxen and accepted a note for £35. When Kerr attempted to collect the debt, Rogers claimed that since he was a minor under the age of twenty-one and still under the government of his mother, the note was null and void. The plaintiff pointed out that Rogers was only about twenty days short of his twenty-first birthday at the time the note was written and, moreover, was the father of three children. The defendant lost and was forced to pay the debt together with court costs of £2-1-8.7 In another case, Joseph Rogers v. Jonathan Beckwith, November 1758, by debt of note, the plaintiff sued for £2-15 on neglect of defendant to make 40 rods of 6-rail-fence for Rogers.8 The court received evidence that in 1754 Daniel Beckwith was appointed by the Lyme selectmen as overseer over his son Jonathan under terms of the statute "for Relieving & ordering Idiots Impotent Distracted & Idle Persons." Since the defendant was under the care of an overseer, he had no right to contract debts and Beckwith recovered court costs of £2-17-5.9 Similarly, Daniel Worthington of Montville successfully sued the town of Colchester in 1806 to pay for medical and funeral expenses for Daniel Brown, a foreigner who was a soldier in Burgoyne's army captured in October 1777. He got drunk and died at the house of the plaintiff.10 In another case that same session, the leaders of the Masonic Lodge in New London sued Moses Warren of Lyme for $24 for nonpayment of his share in purchasing a lot for a hall.11
In the 19th century, the number of debt cases for modest sums is partially superseded by smaller numbers of suits filed by merchants and store keepers, sometimes containing detailed lists of precisely what is owed for each product purchased. In March 1817, Joshua R. Warren and Peter Comstock of Lyme sued John A. Smith of Waterford for $90 of book debts for molasses, nails, pearl ash, rum, sugar, tobacco, and notes paid by the merchants to a number of men and Ezra Maynard of Lyme for $80 on an unspecified "Balance due on Book."12 In addition, many defendants defaulted in the majority of debt cases and, beginning in 1809, such are usually found in separate bound volumes called Defaults.
Debt cases provide extremely useful information for those seeking to gain an understanding of the economy of local towns and patterns of trade. Merchants and shopkeepers from New London County purchased goods from merchants located primarily in Boston, New York City, and Newport. By the mid-eighteenth century, however, merchants from the ports of New London, Norwich, Lyme, Saybrook, Groton, and Stonington had dealings with merchants in the West Indies and these trade patterns are well documented in court papers. In addition, the economic lives of small shopkeepers can also be documented.
At a time when few, if any, records for New London County merchants exist, court records provide extensive information on patterns of trade and economic development. Most traders imported goods from merchants in larger cities, but a surprising amount of trade with the West Indies existed, together with lesser amounts with the Canadian Maritimes and the British Isles. Court records from the beginning of the eighteenth century to 1774 contain around 360 cases concerning the shipping trade and most give the name of the vessel. Researchers can get a bird's eye view of the subject from them. In addition, Files contain more than 160 cases in which the defendant, serving as the plaintiff's bailiff and receiver, failed to uphold his part of the agreement.13 In a November 1774 case, Jeremiah Colver v. Alpheus Davison, the plaintiff asked for a reasonable account of the time the defendant was his bailiff and receiver for one hogshead of rum to be transported from New London to New York City.14
The following cases provide an overview of the kinds of material on trade that can be found in New London County Court Files. James Rogers v. Richard Durfey. In 1738, the defendant, owner of the sloop Two Josephs, was about to embark on a voyage from New London to Ireland, from Ireland to Surinam, and back to New London. The defendant hired Rogers' apprentice Edmund Haynes to serve as ship's cooper, but failed to pay the master wages due of £50-17 shillings.15 William Allen, Ralph Cross, and Jabez True, as joint owners of the sloop Elisabeth worth £500, v. Nathaniel Milbury. The plaintiffs hired the defendant to be master of the Elisabeth in April 1755 to transport English troops from Massachusetts to Nova Scotia, to take 240 Acadians to Virginia, and then return to Massachusetts. Milbury, however, after delivering the French neutrals to Virginia, sailed to the West Indies and during the voyage lost all the ship's anchors and cables and allowed the sails and riggings to rot. The plaintiffs sued for £300 damages and recovered judgment for £72.16 Abiel Cheney and Amasa Ives v. Lemuel Butler. In July 1770, the plaintiffs from Norwich, owners of the schooner Joly Robbin, and defendant from Chilmark, Mass. made an agreement by which the plaintiffs would carry the defendant, four passengers, tools, and merchandise to Martha's Vineyard and the defendant would proceed to use the vessel on a fishing voyage off Nantucket. The defendant, however, failed to go on the fishing voyage and was found guilty to damages of £30.17 In June 1769, the county court heard the case of John Bolles v. James Mumford. The plaintiff of Charlestown, Mass. sued the defendant, stating that he his brother Robinson Mumford, traders in company at Martinique, had refused to pay an order to Bolles for 800 Spanish milled dollars. The court found the defendant guilty and ordered him to pay the plaintiff £142-0-3 damages and £1-12-9 costs. The original bill of exchange is included in the documentation.18
Information on merchants and trade is equally extensive for the period after the American Revolution, although the number of court filings per year for the period 1810-55 is less than half the rate for 1781-1809, a clear reflection of the decline of overseas trade after the War of 1812.19 To the extent that court cases in any way serve as a proxy for overall trade, then the decade 1800-1809 was the time of greatest mercantile activity from New London County ports. The court heard 136 cases during the time period. Although the bulk of trade followed pre-war patterns, a handful of lawsuits featured more exotic locations, such as Canton, China (1789); Anticipation Island in the "South Sea" (1820) Cape Town, South Africa (1835); Matamoros, Mexico (1836); New Zealand (1844); Tristan de Cunha (1844); and California (1850).20
The court also heard seventeen suits brought by ship masters, captains, or owners against mariners who violated the federal statute for regulating seamen in merchant service, most between June 1795 and December 1807. In the first such case, Edward, John, and Robert Hallam of New London sued Willard alias William Miller of Stonington. Miller had contracted to sail on the Hope for a voyage from New London to Liverpool and return for $15 per month. The owners advanced Miller one month's wages, but he deserted prior to sailing. The plaintiffs recovered £4-10 damages and £3-5-6 costs.21 Also discovered were some sixteen lawsuits involving sealing or whaling voyages between December 1820 and June 1851. Three cases date from the June 1835 court session.22 In one lawsuit, Charles F. Lester and John P. Huntington sued the Union Insurance Company of New London for $8,000. The Atlas encountered a violent storm in the South Atlantic, was severely damaged, and sailed to the Cape of Good Hope for $3,000 of repairs. The court found for the plaintiffs and the insurance company appealed to the Superior Court.
The records contain around 285 cases for the post-Revolutionary era in which plaintiffs sued parties who served as their bailiffs and receivers. Lawsuits that specifically relate to merchant shipping are not included in this total. Five cases brought before the June 1810 court typify the pattern. Two concerns notes and money and three goods, wares, and merchandise. One involved the transport and sale of 5,000 pounds of cheese in the West Indies and a second brandy, rum, sugar, and other items to damages of $4,000.23 As economic activity became more dominated by larger firms, bills of exchange became more common and some handsome samples are occasionally found in the records, as in David Ludlow et al v. John Coles. The New York merchants sued to collect $12,000 per bill of exchange. The defendant defaulted and the plaintiffs recovered $19,688.52 damages and $13.24 costs.24